The Barbara W. Streeten MD Papers
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The Barbara W. Streeten MD Papers
1971-2015
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Streeten, Barbara W.
2.92 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of Barbara W. Streeten, who was a Professor of Ophthalmology and Pathology at SUNY Upstate Medical University in Syracuse, NY. The collection has four series: Writings, Subject Files, Photographs, and Posters.
2017.0006
Biographical Note
Barbara Anne Wiard Streeten (1925-2015) was an American ophthalmologist known for her research contributions on pseudoexfoliative disease of the lens, the protein composition of the zonule, and ocular finding in many genetic disorders. She was born in Derry, New Hampshire in 1925 and raised in Revere, Massachusetts, where she was valedictorian of Revere High School at the age of 16. In 1945, she received her A.B. (magna cum laude) at the age of 20 from Tufts University followed by her M.D. (cum laude) in 1950 from Tufts University Medical School. Tufts University awarded her the medical Alumni Association Prize in Physiology in 1947 and the Medical Alumni Association Prize in Pathology, Bacteriology, and Parasitology in 1948. She completed residencies in pathology at Boston City Hospital and in Ophthalmology at Wayne County Hospital and the University of Michigan followed by a fellowship in Ophthalmic Pathology at the Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary.
Dr. Streeten was an ophthalmology faculty member at the University of Michigan from 1956 to 1960, but moved to Syracuse in 1960 with her husband Dr. David H.P. Streeten, who was a prominent endocrinologist and faculty member at SUNY Upstate Medical University for 50 years. Dr. Streeten joined Upstate as an Ophthalmology and Pathology faculty member in 1964 and was Director of the Eye Pathology Laboratory from 1967 to 2008. She received her first NIH grant in 1975 for research on the structure of the ocular zonule entitled “The Fiber-Gel Structure of the Ocular Zonule” and was continuously funded for 27 years. She retired at the age of 83 after having authored more than 120 journal articles and book chapters, with 68 published abstracts. Her honors include the SUNY President’s Award for Excellence and Leadership in Research in 2000, the SUNY Chancellor’s Award for Excellence in Scholarship and Creative Activities in 2005. She was also awarded the Zimmerman Medal in 1997, the highest honor in Ophthalmic Pathology.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the personal papers of Barbara W. Streeten that relate to her research and career as a Professor of Ophthalmology and Pathology at SUNY Upstate Medical University. There are four series in this collection.
Writings: these papers contain Dr. Streeten's publications, research materials for publications, and corresponding materials for publications, including notes, forms, correspondence, and photographs from the late 1970s to 2000s.
Subject Files: these records contain Dr. Streeten's research materials from the late 1970s to 1990s. These were primarily for publications, but there are also materials for unpublished papers, such as manuscript drafts and notes, correspondence, and photographs.
Photographs: these materials consist of research photographs from the 1980s and 1990s, including ones reproduced in publications, and print photographs of Dr. Streeten from 1976.
Posters: this series consists of digital photographs of Dr. Streeten's scientific posters that primarily were displayed at conferences before the research information was published.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Barbara W. Streeten MD Papers have been arranged into four series.
Subject and Genre Headings
Streeten, Barbara W.; Ophthalmology; Pathology; State University of New York Health Science Center at Syracuse; SUNY Upstate Medical University; Upstate Medical University (N.Y.)
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Department of Ophthalmology in 2017.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Aberrant Synthesis of EMP-COTS-PSX: Aberrant Synthesis and Aggregation of Elastic Components in Pseudoexfoliative Fibrillopathy: An Unifying Concept, 1993 (Box Box 1)
  - Rotary Shadowing Paper – Fig. 2 Zonule, c. 1991 (Box Box 1)
  - The Nature of the Ocular Zonule, Thesis, 1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudomelanoma of the Iris in H. Simplex Keratoiritis, 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Potato Gun Ocular Injury Reprints, 1998 (Box Box 1)
  - Precapsular Film on the Aging Human Lens Precursor of Pseudoexfoliation?, 1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Posterior Keratoconus Associated with Systemic Abnormalities, 1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Phacoanaphylactoid Reaction in Persistent Hyperplastic Primary Vitreous, Caudill, BWS, Tso, 1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Pathobiology of Ocular Disease: A Dynamic Approach, 1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Ocular Involvement in Familial Erythrophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis, 1997 (Box Box 1)
  - Ocular Findings in Kenny’s Syndrome, 1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Necrobiotic Xanthogranuloma with IgA Multiple Myeloma: A Case Report and Literature Review, 1990-1991 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudoexfoliative Fibrillopathy in the Skin of Patients with Ocular Pseudoexfoliation, 1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Preinvasive Carcinoma of the Cornea and Conjunctiva, 1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Molluscum Contagiosum of the Eyelids in Patients with Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome, 1992 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudomelanoma of the Iris in Herpes Simplex Keratoiritis, 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudoexfoliative Material Contains an Elastic Microfibrillar-Associated Glycoprotein, 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudoexfoliation Syndrome Chapter, 1994 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudoexfoliative Fibrillopathy in Visceral Organs of a Patient with PSX Syndrome, 1992-1993 (Box Box 1)
  - Pseudoexfoliative Material and Oxytalan Fibers, BWS, AJ Dark, C. Barnes, 1984 (Box Box 1)
  - Proboscis Lateralis with Associated Orbital Cyst: Detailed Mr and CT Imaging and Correlative Embryopathy, 1992 (Box Box 1)
  - Posterior Zonules and Lens Extraction, 1978 (Box Box 1)
  - Zonular Apparatus Chapter, 1992 (Box Box 1)
  - Vitreous Asteroid Bodies, 1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Traumatic Episcleritis Following Phosphorus 32 Testing, 1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Rotary Shadowing of Elastic System Microfibrils in the Ocular Zonule, Vitreous, and Ligamentum Nuchae, 1991 (Box Box 1)
  - Radiation-Induced Atrophy of the Meibomian Glands, 1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Microfibrillar Protein and Phospholipid in Granular Corneal Dystrophy, 1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Malignant Teratoid Medulloepithelioma in an Adult, 1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Localized Conjunctival Amyloidosis Associated with Extranodal Lymphoma, 1987 (Box Box 1)
  - Lens Capsule Abnormalities in Alport’s Syndrome, 1987 (Box Box 1)
  - Lectin Binding to Pseudoexfoliative Material and the Ocular Zonules, 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Inverted Papilloma of the Conjunctiva, 1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Immunolocalization of Big-h3 Protein in 5q31-Linked Corneal Dystrophies and Normal Corneas, 1999 (Box Box 1)
  - Immunohistochemical Comparison of Ocular Zonules and the Microfibrils of Elastic Tissue, 1981 (Box Box 1)
  - Identification of Extractable Proteins from the Bovine Ocular Zonule: Major Zonular Antigens of 32kD and 250kD, 1988 (Box Box 1)
  - Human Posterior Subcapsular Cataract, 1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Fungal Growth in Aphakic Soft Contact Lenses, 1981 (Box Box 1)
  - Exfoliation Syndrome in a 17-Year-Old Girl, 1997 (Box Box 1)
  - Energy Dispersive X-ray Analysis of the Cornea, 1984 (Box Box 1)
  - Elastic Fiber Components and Protease Inhibitors in Pinguecula, 1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Elastosis of the Lamina Cribrosa in PSX Syndrome with Glaucoma, 1995 (Box Box 1)
  - Disorders of the Vitreous Chapter in Pathobiology of Ocular Disease Part B, 1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Disorders of the Vitreous Chapter Part A, 1994 (Box Box 1)
  - Corneal Transplantation in Familial Dysautonomia, 1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Corneal Rupture in the Neonate: Management and Pathology Reprints, 1988 (Box Box 1)
  - Burkitt Lymphoma Presenting as a Conjunctival Mass, 1994 (Box Box 1)
  - “Blue-Body” Epithelial Cell Inclusions in Conjunctivitis, 1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1987 (Box Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1984-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1983-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1980-1981 (Box Box 2)
  - Anatomy of the Zonular Apparatus, c. 1992 (Box Box 2)
  - Amyloidosis of the Vitreous, 1982 (Box Box 2)
  - Amyloid P Protein in Pseudoexfoliative Fibrillopathy, 1989 (Box Box 2)
  - Abnormal Scleral Collagen in Nanophthalmos, 1991 (Box Box 2)
  - Reprints, 1982 (Box Box 2)
  - Reprints, 1971 (Box Box 2)
  - PSX Chapter, Schlotzer-Schrehardt and Streeten, 2006-2007 (Box Box 2)
  - Association of Elastin with PSX Material, 1988 (Box Box 2)
  - Publications, 1977-2006; 2 folders (Box Box 2)
  - HNK-1 Paper, 1994-1996 (Box Box 2)
  - HNK-1 Paper, 1991; 1993; 1996-1997 (Box Box 3)
  - HNK-1 Papers, 1985-1993; 1995; 1997 (Box Box 3)
  - Archives of Ophthalmology, HNK-1 Epitope in the Lens-Ciliary Zonular Region in Normal and PSX Eyes, 1996-1997 (Box Box 3)
  - Current reprints, HNK-1, 1997 (Box Box 3)
  - Alports, lens capsule paper, 1987 (Box Box 3)
  - BWS thesis for AOS, Nature of the Ocular Zonules, c. 1982 (Box Box 3)
- Subject Files
  - Kagan, Herbert, Lysyl Oxidase project, 1994-1999 (Box Box 3)
  - Lysyl Oxidase in PSX, 1996-1999 (Box Box 3)
  - Poster I.S.E.R., Pathological Changes in Aging Eyes, 1980 (Box Box 4)
  - Fibrillin and HNK, 1992-1994 (Box Box 4)
  - Fibrilla poster, ARVO prints, 1986-1987 (Box Box 4)
  - Fibrillin poster, 1987; 1989-1991 (Box Box 4)
  - 3 year conj biopsy, 1996-1998 (Box Box 4)
  - Letters, 1996 (Box Box 4)
  - Lens chapter, 1979; undated (Box Box 4)
  - Lens research, 1979; 1987; 1990-1991 (Box Box 5)
  - Cornea research, 1999 (Box Box 5)
  - Retina, vitreous research, 1978; undated; 2 folders (Box Box 5)
  - Macula SEM research, 1978; 1984; 1991; undated (Box Box 5)
  - Melanoma case, undated (Box Box 5)
  - Trabeculeum [Trabecula] and ciliary body research, elastic fibers, 1984; 1988-1989; 1994 (Box Box 6)
  - PSX archive, 1990-1991; 1996-2000 (Box Box 6)
  - Corneal dystrophies, 1976; 1978-1980; 1989; 1995 (Box Box 6)
  - Turcot’s Syndrome (Final) with Adrenal Adenomata and an Atypical Inverted Mucoepidermoid Papilloma of Conjunctiva, 1987; 1992-1994 (Box Box 6)
  - Obituary and C.V., 2015; undated (Box Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Cultured lens epithelium, 1988 (Box Box 7)
  - Cultured skin, 1990-1992 (Box Box 7)
  - Osteosarcoma, 1986 (Box Box 7)
  - Rat Smooth Muscle Cells, 1986 (Box Box 7)
  - Swift skin, 1985; 1988; 1990 (Box Box 7)
  - PSX conj culture, Fibrillin, 1992 (Box Box 7)
  - Cultured nonpigmented epithelium, 1986; 1988 (Box Box 7)
  - Cultured calf lens cells, 1987; 1991 (Box Box 7)
  - Ophthalmology 35mm negatives, 1967 (Box Box 7)
  - Pathology slides and charts 35mm negatives, 1977-1978 (Box Box 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box Box 7)
  - Portrait photographs of Dr. Streeten, 1976 (Box Box 7)
- Posters
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated
  - undated